Last video we had a look at the dlmalloc implementation of free().
上一个视频我们，看了 free() 的 dlmalloc实现。
We discovered the unlink() macro that can be used to write almost arbitrary data to
我们发现了 unlink() 宏，可以用来将几乎任意的数据写入
another address.
另一个地址。
We constructed a proof of concept heap with gdb and observed a successful write to the
我们用gdb构造了一个堆的实践，
global offset table.
并观察到了，一个对全局偏移表的成功写入。
But eventually we realized, that our plan wouldn’t work, because it contains too many
但最终我们意识到，我们的计划行不通，因为它包含了太多
null-bytes and we can’t write those with strcpy.
null字节，我们不能用strcpy编写这些字节。
Let’s quickly recap and summarize what we know about the heap and the free algorithm
让我们快速回顾和总结一下，我们对堆和free 算法的了解，
to refine our exploitation plan.
完善我们的开发计划。
The last video was more explorative, taking you along how you could discover the exploit
上一视频更具探索性，让你可以自己发现漏洞。
yourself, but this video will be more of a presentation.
但这段视频更像是一个演示。
This way we have to different styles of video about the same topic, which I hope increases
这样，我们就有了关于同一主题，不同风格的视频，
the amount of people who understand how it works.
我希望能增加，了解它工作原理的人数。
So let’s look again at how a heap chunk looks like.
我们再来看看堆区块的样子。
When you allocate a chunk of a certain size, the size of the chunk will be written to the
当您分配某大小的块时，
2nd word and malloc will return the address here.
该块的大小将写入第二个字，和 malloc将在这里返回地址。
This means you have this area for user data.
意味着，您拥有了用户数据的区域。
The last bits of the chunk size have special meaning.
块大小的最后一位，具有特殊意义。
Most importantly the last bit is the previous in use bit.
最重要的是，最后一位，是前一个是否正在使用的描述。
So that is information about the chunk BEFORE the current chunk.
这是关于当前块，前面的块信息。
So that’s a little bit weird to wrap your head around at the beginning.
所以在开始的时候，把头包起来有点奇怪。
This means if this block here is allocated, the block after wards would have the last
这意味着，如果这分配了第一个块，
bit set.
那么后面的块，将具有最后一个设置位。
Because the chunk in front of it is in use.
因为，它前面的块，正在使用中。
Now a free chunk could contain more information.
现在，一个空闲块可以包含更多信息。
So once we free this chunk, we obviously can set the last bit of the chunk afterwards to
所以，一旦我们释放了这个块，很明显我们可以
0.
将块的最后一位设置为0。
To indicate that the previous chunk is not in use anymore.
以指示上一块不再使用。
Now imagine there is a third chunk.
现在，假设有第三块。
A chunk after the 2nd one, which has it’s previous in use bit NOT set.
第二个块之后的块，它的最后位没有设置。
This means the 2nd chunk is free.
这意味着，第二个块是空闲的。
Now the algorithm would like to merge, consolidate those two blocks.
现在，算法要合并，合并这两个块。
This is where the two words after the size start being important.
这就是 size 后的两个词，开始变得重要的地方。
They are the forward and backward pointer.
它们其实是向前和向后的指针。
Just as a sidenote, this only applies to chunks that are bigger than the fastbin size.
正如旁注，只适用于，大于fastbin大小的块。
Because fastbins are very small chunks and they don’t use a double linked list.
因为，FastBins是非常小的块，它们不使用双链表。
So our chunks are bigger.
所以，我们的块更大。
Let’s consider this heap setup.
让我们考虑一下，这个堆设置。
We have a chunk we want to free, which is followed by an already free chunk.
我们有一个要释放的块，后面跟着一个已经释放的块。
And that free chunk has two pointers, forward and backwards pointing to some other free
这个空闲块有两个指针，向前和向后(指针)指向另一个空闲块
chunks.
块。
So they are in this double linked list.
所以，它们在这个双链表中。
Now what will happen is, the free algorithm will merge these two blocks together.
现在会发生的是，free 算法将这两个块合并在一起。
It will do that by first unlinking the free block from the linked list, by using the unlink
它将首先用“unlink”宏，从链表中断开空闲块。
macro.
宏。
And we learned what it does, it takes the forward pointing address and writes it at
我们学过了它所做的，它拿起向前指针的地址，
the forward pointer of the previous chunk.
写入前一个块的向前指针。
And it will take the backward pointing address and write it to the backward pointer of the
再把向后指针的地址，写入
next chunk.
下一个块的向后指针。
And when we obviously control the pointers of a free chunk that will be unlinked, we
当我们明确控制了一个空闲块的指针，它将被断链，
can point into the global offset table and write there the forward address.
我们可以指向GOT，并在其中写入向前地址。
In the last video we stopped here and didn’t check out what happens next.
在上一段视频中，我们停在这里，没有查看接下来会发生什么。
But let me tell you now.
但，我现在告诉你。
So next we will increase the size of the chunk we are freeing with the size of the already
接下来，我们用已经空闲块的size，
free block.
增加我们正要释放的块大小。
And then we will insert this block into the double linked list.
然之后，我们将这个块插入到双链表中。
Which means we take one chunk, and look up it’s forward chunk.
这意味着，我们取了一块，并查找它的前一个块。
And then we update the pointers accordingly to now include our chunk.
然后，我们更新相应的指针，让其现在包含块。
This is the whole magic of the heap.
这就是堆的全部魔力。
Now let’s go back to the famous phrack articles “Once upon a free” and “vudo malloc
现在让我们回到，著名的短语文章“Once upon a free”和“Vudo malloc 诡计“
tricks” to see what they tell us about the unlink exploit.
看看他们，告诉我们关于 unlink 的漏洞。
Both articles contain a cool little trick to overcome the limitations of the null-byte.
这两篇文章，都包含一个很酷的小技巧，来克服null字节的限制。
So when we want to construct a fake chunk that we can unlink, we want to make sure that
因此，当我们想要构造一个可以 unlink 的假块时，
no field has to contain a null-byte.
我们要确保任何字段，都不包含null字节。
This means we have to use very very large values for the size.
这意味着，我们必须对大小使用非常大的值。
But that doesn’t seem useful, because the heap is not that big.
但这似乎没用，因为堆没那么大。
Mh.
呃
But the clever idea showed in the phrack articles make use of how computers handle negative
但是在文章中展示的聪明做法是，
values.
让计算机处理负值。
So let’s quickly explore what happens with a 32bit integer value, when we add a very
因此，让我们快速探索32位整数值，会发生什么，
very large number.
当我们添加一个很好的数。
For example fffffffC.
例如，fffffffc。
That would be over 4 billion.
那将超过40亿。
Now what happens when you add 0x64, which is decimal 100 to that 4 billion?
现在，当你加上0x64时，会发生什么，它是十进制的 100 加到40亿上？
That doesn’t fit in 32bit.
这不适合32位。
And the carry of the addition will be lost.
加在一起的东西，会丢失。
And now you have a very small value again.
现在，你又有了一个非常小的值。
In fact it’s 0x60.
事实上，它是0x60。
Which is 4 less than 0x64.
比 0x64 小 4。
This means by adding 4 billion, the ffffffc to 100, we actually subtracted 4.
这意味着，加上40亿，ffffffc加100，我们实际上，剩下4。
And that’s a really useful behaviour for our case.
这对我们来说，是非常有用的行为。
Because this value that doesn’t contain any null-bytes behaves like a very small subtraction.
因为这个不包含任何null字节的值，它的行为类似一个非常小的减法。
So when we skim over the sourcecode again, we can now make a plan.
所以，当我们再次浏览源代码时，我们现在可以制定一个计划。
First of all we again have to overflow the size of our chunk with a bigger value than
首先，我们必须用一个溢出块大小的值，
80.
大于80。
So let’s do the 100 like last video.
所以让我们像上一个视频一样使用100。
But then we could also not care about the first consolidation attempt of the previous
但是，我们也不关心前一块的合并尝试
block.
块。
This ways we don’t have to setup another fake chunk.
这样，我们就不必设置另一个假块。
So we make sure that the last bit of the block we are going to free is set to 1.
所以，我们要确保我们要释放的块的，最后一个位设置为1。
So it’s still in use.
所以，它还在使用中。
But we could do the consolidate forward part.
但，我们可以合并向前部分。
There we take the next chunk and check from it’s next chunk the prev in use bit, and
在这里，我们拿起下一个块，检查它的下一个块的前in_use位，
if that is not set, we attempt to unlink, consolidate that block.
如果没有设置，我们将尝试 unlink，合并该块。
This means we need two fake blocks, one that contains the forward and backwards pointer
这意味着，我们需要两个假块，一个包含向前和向后指针，
we want to use to overwrite the GoT with an address from the heap.
用堆中的地址覆盖got。
And the second chunk has to have a size with the lowest bit set to 0.
第二个块，必须有一个最低位设置为0的size。
BUT we can’t use small size values.
但,我们不能使用小尺寸的值。
But if you look in the code how size is used, it’s just used as an offset which is added
但是，如果您在代码中，查看 size 是如何使用的，它只是用作一个偏移量，
to an address.
添加到一个地址。
The code doesn’t check that it’s a ridiculous huge chunk.
代码并没有检查，它是否是一个荒谬的超大块。
It just adds that value.
它只是增加了这个值。
And here is where the trick comes into play.
这就是诡计发挥的地方。
We could use fffffffc as the size of the chunk, which results in a -4.
我们可以使用 fffffc 作为块的大小，结果是-4。
Now think what will happen.
现在，想想会发生什么。
It will take the size of that chunk, adds it to the current address to find the next
它将占用该块的 size，并将其添加到当前地址，以查找下一个块，
chunk, which fools free into thinking the next chunk is at -4 from here.
愚弄 free ，让它认为下一个块在这里的 -4。
Now it will read the size of that chunk, which we could also set to fffffffc, which doesn’t
现在，它将读取该块的大小，我们也可以将其设置为 fffffffc，
have the last bit set and concludes, yep, the block before was not in use, let’s unlink
不会设置最后一个位并断定，之前块没有使用，。
it.
所以让我们 unlink它吧。
And booom!
爆炸！
It’s very beautiful and clever.
漂亮，聪明的手段。
And doesn’t contain any null bytes.
并且，不包含任何null字节。
So let’s see if we can fill that heap in a way that we can do that with strcpys.
那么，让我们看看我们是否可以用strcpy，来填充这个堆。
So strcpy stops at a null-byte.
所以，strcpy 在一个null字节处 停止。
This means we have to use one of them to overflow the size of the chunk we want to free with
这意味着，我们必须使用其中一个 strcpy，来溢出我们想要释放的块大小。
100, 0x64.
100，0x64。
Ehh.. obviously we want to prev in use bit set, so we need to overflow it with 0x65.
嗯… 显然，我们想要前块的设置位，所以，我们需要用0x65溢出它。
This works because we don’t want to write more than that, it ends in a null byte and
有效，因为我们不想写更多，它以一个null字节结束，
keeps the size clean.
并且保持 size 干净。
The other strcpy could be used to fill up the 100 byte until the weird conjoined fake
另一个 strcpy 可以用来填充100字节，直到奇怪的，假的，连体块
chunks with ffffc, and afterwards the two addresses we want to write.
ffffc，之后，就是我们要写的两个地址。
Now like in the previous video we will set the one address to the global offset table,
现在，就像在上一个视频中一样，我们将把一个地址设置为全局偏移表，
so that we overwrite puts, and the other one will be pointing into the first heap.
这样我们就覆盖了puts，而另一个，将指向第一个堆。
This means we will redirect code execution to this heap address and we can use the first
这意味着，我们将把代码执行重定向到这个堆地址，
strcpy to place some shellcode here.
并且可以使用第一个strcpy，在这里放置一些shellcode。
Keep in mind that the unlink will also write some data from the global offset table to
请记住，unlink 也会将一些数据，从全局偏移表写入这堆区域，
this heap area, so we have to either keep the shellcode short, or jump over the smashed
所以我们要么保持 shellcode 简短，
data and continue shellcode afterwards.
要么跳过粉碎的，之后继续 shellcode。
But we just want to call winner.
但我们只想调用 winner。
So let’s construct the exploit.
那么让我们来构建这个漏洞。
You could do it in one line, but let me break it up to makeit easier to follow.
你可以一行搞定，但让我把它拆开，让它更容易。
In each of these windows we will construct one parameter, one string for each strcpy.
这些窗口中，我们将为每个strcpy，构造一个参数和一个字符串。
So maybe let’s first take care of the strcpy of the middle chunk, because that should be
所以，也许我们先来处理中间块的strcpy，
the one to overwrite the chunk size with 101 of the 3rd chunk.
因为它应该是，被第三个块的101覆盖的。
I use echo for that and I counted the amount of characters necessary to hit the size of
我用 echo 来表示，我计算了触碰到块 size 的字符数，
the chunk, where we then write 101, 0x65.
然后，我们在这里写101，0x65。
I redirect the output into a file B, and then we can use it with backticks and cat as a
我将输出重定向到一个文件B中，然后，我们可以将它，带上 backticks和cat一起，
parameter in gdb.
用作 gdb中的参数。
We can then run it and investigate the heap.
然后，我们可以运行它，并调查堆。
Looks perfect, the size of the third chunk is now 0x65.
看起来很完美，第三个块的大小现在是 0x65。
Next let’s take care of the third chunk, which is after the overflow, so it’s 100
接下来，我们来处理第三个块，它现在是溢出之后，
byte big.
所以是，100字节大。
So we want to write like 100 characters to fill the chunk and then eventually we arrive
所以，我们想写100个字符来填充块，
at the next chunk, where we want to write the fffffc’s for the trick from earlier,
然后最终到达下一块，这里我们用前面的技巧 fffffc 写入，
followed by the global offset table address and the heap address.
后面是全局偏移表地址，和堆地址。
Here I get the table address for puts and subtract -12 from it.
这里我得到了 puts 的表地址，并从中减去-12。
Because the heap address will be written at +12.
因为堆地址写成 +12。
And then comes the last strcpy, the first chunk, where we want to include our shellcode
然后，是最后一个strcpy，第一个块，我们想在其中，包含shellcode
to call winner.
调用winner 。
I quickly googled for an online assembler to create the shellcode.
我很快在谷歌上，搜索了一个在线汇编程序，来创建shellcode。
We want to call an absolute address, to do this we have to go via a register.
我们要调用一个绝对地址，要做到这一点，我们必须通过一个寄存器。
So we could move the address of winner into eax and then call eax.
所以，我们可以把 winner 的地址移到eax中，然后调用eax。
We can simply copy the string representation of this shellcode and write it into the A
我们可以简单复制这个shellcode的字符串表示形式，
file.
并将其写入文件A。
Cool.
酷。
Now that we have all thre parameters we can rerun the program.
既然我们有了所有的三个参数，就可以重新运行程序了。
So Let’s have a look at the heap.
让我们来看看堆。
It looks nice.
看起来不错。
Let’s execute the free and single step into the puts call.
让我们执行 free ，并单步进到 puts调用中。
Oh.
哦。
great we follow into the heap, but somehow our shellcode is wrong.
太好了，我们继续往下看，但不知何故，我们的 shellcode 是错误的。
You can see that it’s complete garbage.
你可以看到它完全是垃圾。
Instead of our shellcode we have some addresses here.
这里没有我们的 shellcode ，而是有一些地址。
Oouh!
哎哟！
Of course, we perform multiple frees, not just the one.
当然，我们执行多个 free，而不仅仅是一个。
So we obviously write metadata over these values.
所以，我们显然是在这些值上写元数据的。
But we can simply fix that by pointing to a different area of the heap.
但，我们可以简单解决这个问题，通过指向堆的不同区域。
How about here at 14.
14，怎么样？
Now we change the address and prepend some characters to our shellcode. and try it again.
现在我们更改地址，并在 shellcode 前面加上一些字符。然后再试一次。
We run it, single step into puts and arrive at winner.
我们一路运行，步进到 puts，最终获得 winner。
hehe.
哈哈哈。
Let’s try it without GDB!
让我们在没有gdb的情况下，试试吧！
It worked.
它奏效了。
Gosh I love this!
天哪，我喜欢这个！